<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true copy of the Latine oration of the excellent Lord George Ossolinski, Count Palatine of Tenizyn, and Sendomyria, Chamberlain to the Kings Maiestie of Poland, and Suethland, and embassadour to the Kings most excellent Maiesty As it was pronounced to his Maiestie at White-Hall by the said embassadour, on Sunday the 11. of March. 1620. With the translation of the same into English. Commanded by his Maiestie to be published in print.</title>
            <title>True copy of the Latine oration of the excellent Lord George Ossolinski. English and Latin</title>
            <author>Ossoliński, Jerzy, 1595-1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08570</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18890</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113595</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848828</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848828</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13944</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08570)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13944)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 968:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true copy of the Latine oration of the excellent Lord George Ossolinski, Count Palatine of Tenizyn, and Sendomyria, Chamberlain to the Kings Maiestie of Poland, and Suethland, and embassadour to the Kings most excellent Maiesty As it was pronounced to his Maiestie at White-Hall by the said embassadour, on Sunday the 11. of March. 1620. With the translation of the same into English. Commanded by his Maiestie to be published in print.</title>
                  <title>True copy of the Latine oration of the excellent Lord George Ossolinski. English and Latin</title>
                  <author>Ossoliński, Jerzy, 1595-1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed [By George Purslowe] for William Lee: and are to be sold at his shop in Fleetstreet, neere Sergeants Inne, at the signe of the golden Bucke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Latin text followed by an English translation.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>The italic text on A3r to A4v is in two settings: A3r third line from bottom has (1) "Ottomanarum" or (2) "Ottomanorum".</note>
                  <note>Knuttel I:3159 lists a Dutch translation stating "Na de copy, ghedruct te Londen by B. Norton ende J. Bill".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery ("Early English books, 1475-1640", reel 968), and the british Library ("Early English newspapers", unit 24, reel 1153).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Poland --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Poland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13944:1"/> 
               <pb facs="tcp:13944:1"/> A TRVE COPY OF THE LATINE ORATION OF THE EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Lord <hi>George Oſſolinski,</hi> Count <hi>Palatine</hi> of
<hi>Tenizyn,</hi> and <hi>Sendomyria,</hi> Chamberlain to the Kings Maieſtie of <hi>Poland,</hi> and <hi>Suethland,</hi> and Embaſſadour to the Kings moſt Excellent MAIESTY.</p>
            <p>As it was pronounced to his MAIESTIE at <hi>White-Hall</hi> by the ſaid Embaſſadour, on Sunday <hi>the</hi> 11. <hi>of March.</hi> 1620.</p>
            <p>With the Tranſlation of the ſame into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>Commanded by his Maieſtie to be publiſhed in Print.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of William Lee (similar to Robert Estienne's) with olive tree, branches falling and a man</figDesc>
               <q>NOLI ALTVM SAPERE</q>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>William Lee:</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in Fleetſtreet, neere Sergeants Inne, at the ſigne of the golden Bucke. 1621.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13944:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13944:2"/>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sereniſsime <hi>REX,</hi>
                  </salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAcra, Regia Poloniae, &amp; Sueciae Maieſtas, Dominus meus clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimus integram diuturnam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem, foeliciſsimos votorum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium euentus, florens ac tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum latiſsimarum ditionum Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> M. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. <hi>precatus, ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem fraterni animi, &amp; rerum,</hi> M. V. <hi>ſtudioſiſsimi, propenſionem, max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imà quà poteſt particularis ergà</hi> M. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. <hi>affectus teſtificatione declarat, ac his obſtring it literis. Quibus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiis, vt reliqua Legationis meae ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedienti mihi,</hi> M. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. <hi>benignas au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res praebere dignetur, humilimè poſtulo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Andem erupt Ottomanarum iam diu cela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum pectore virus, &amp; depoſitâ ſimulatae multis abhinc annis amicitiae laruâ, publico
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13944:3"/> Barbarorum furore, validiſsimum Chriſtiani orbis antemuräle, petitur Polonia. Perſtrepit bellico appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratu Oriens, onerantur claſsibus maria, iungitur Europae Aſia, Africanarum ſi quid eſt virium in noſtram armatur perniciem. In ſocietatem tanti belli veniunt haereditarij nominis noſtri hoſtes, Scythiae; venit &amp; vterque Dacus; Seruij, Bulgari, Boſnenſes, Illyrij, Thraces, Epirotae, quicquid ferarum vſquam eſt gentium, vi, praemijs, pollicitationibus, ſpe praedae, cupiditate vindictae cogitur, pellicitur, accenditur. Paratus nuper lamentabilis cruentae tragoediae prolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus; hauſit immitis primum cruorem Dacia, cùm per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidus hoſtis veterum ac recentium ſolenni iureiur ando firmatorum immemor foederum, innumeris copijs Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giae Maieſtatis Domini mei clementiſsimi petens ditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, appoſitam ſibi paruam quidèm, ſed bellicoſiſsimam noſtrorum manum caecîdit, ingenti Chriſtianae Reip. detrimento.</p>
               <p>Creuêru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t etenim eâ victoriâ barbari ſpiritus, &amp; tam fauſtis inſolentes primordijs vniuerſam ſpe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cipiunt Europa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, eô prouecti vel arrogantiae, vel amentiae, vt nec aſſentiente quidem Deo, delere gentem noſtram ſe poſſe arbitrentur. Tanto non ſuarum duntaxat, ſed Chriſtianarum omnium prouinciarum commota ſacra Regia Maieſtas Dominus meus clementiſsimus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimine, eo fuit animo, vt &amp; reliquos Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes impendentis metus commonefaceret, &amp; inprimis <pb n="3" facs="tcp:13944:3"/> ad <hi>M. V.</hi> nullâ interpoſitâ morâ, referret.</p>
               <p>Sed ea eſt <hi>M. V.</hi> ſingularis vigilantia, tantum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munis Chriſtianorum boni ſtudium, vt &amp; illos, ad quos ipſa potiſsimùm vel temporum, vel locorum ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione pertinent pericula, animaduertat. Anteuertit <hi>M. V.</hi> &amp; hunc Sereniſsimi Regis mei nuncium, idque vltrò praeſtitit quod poſtulandum erat, cùm eidem hoſti ſe Regiae M. Domini mei clementiſsimi amicum eſse, nec ei vllo in diſcrimine deeſse poſſe, nunciauit. Quâ in re agnoſcit
<hi>R. M.</hi> verè magnum, verè regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, verè Chriſtianum <hi>M. V.</hi> animum; agnoſcit fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternum ergàſe affectum, quem gratiſsimi teſtificatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne animi proſequitur, ac profitetur, nihil tam graue, nihil tam difficile, nihil tâm periculoſum fore, quod viciſsim <hi>M. V.</hi> cauſâ aggredi recuſet. Moueantur vtinam tam praeclaro <hi>M. V.</hi> exemplo reliqui Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianorum Principes, velintquè potius tam glorioſi la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boris eſſe cooperatores, quàm ſegnes &amp; otioſi ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores alieni periculi, peſſundaturi quandoquè propria, dum vicina negligunt. Id verò vſu venire noſtro, ſi Dijs placet, credant cautiores, exemplo, quos neglecta Graecia, deſerta Pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nonia, in has coniecit anguſtias. Et nos quidèm eam quam coelum tulerit, ſortem feremus, renouaturi Saguntinorum fidei, Tyriorum conſtantiae, &amp; ſi quid vſquam fortiter actum, exempla; caeterùm vicini noſtri prouideant, quaratione animos firmare poſsint, ad fimiles, vel (auertant omen ſuperi) graui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ores
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13944:4"/> caſus tolerandos. Nequè putent tyrannum, euius animuum humiles Sarmatarum caſae ad tam deteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum impulêrunt periurium, ſanctiora habiturum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinitatis iura quae cum eis iecerit, quorum vrbibus mercaturâ florentiſsimis, opibus praeſtantiſsimis, ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dificiorum cultu ſplendidiſsimis, iamdudum inhiat. Non detinebunt haec, ſed allicient, non extinguent, ſed infla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mabunt, ſacrilegam per nefas propagandi imperij ſitim. Quis enim non videt hoc vnum Tyrannum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendere, quod in maioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eius multo tempore agitatum conſtet fuiſſe confilio, vt occupatâ patentiſsimâ in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Europae partes regione, omnis grani feraciſsimâ, omnium ad claſſem inſtruendam, armandamque neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſariorum refertiſsimâ, innumeris ſuis copijs opima apperiat horrea, nauium ingentem praeparet copiam, quibus Balthicum occupet ſinum, tranſiturus in Ocea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, vt ſic binis claſsibus, velut alis, ab vtroquè mar. Europam premat, &amp; opprimat; terreſtres copias per apertiſsimos, quà Poloniam ſpectat, campos, in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniam effundat, quà euntem non montium clauſtra retinere, nonfluminum rapacitas poterit retardare? Voluebat haec Solymannus animo, agitabanteius poſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ri, nec vllâ aliâ ab eo conſilio deterritos eosfuiſſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> conſtatratione, quàm quòd crederent vniuerſos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiraturos Chriſtianos, ad tuendum hoc Regnum, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuius ſalute totius Europae pendeat integritas. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deerantillo uotam magnanimi Principes, qui malu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſent <pb n="5" facs="tcp:13944:4"/> opum, ac vitae propriae detrimentum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, quàm vicini ſibi populi ſalutem pericli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantem deſerere. Haec noſtrâ aetate, proh do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor! multi non intelligunt, negligunt nonnul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, &amp; quod dolendum magis, accerſunt vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trò ad communem omnium perniciem, perſidum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis Chriſtiani hoſtem, indigni Chriſtiano no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, Barbaris ipſis execrabiliores. Vnum Te habent, Sereniſsime Rex, haec noſtra tempora, qui pro ſingulari tuâ prudentiâ animaduertiſti, &amp; iudicâſti per latus Poloniae vniuerſam peti Europam, ac eius periculum ad omnes perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere Chriſtianos; ſolenne Ottomanorum eſſe bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la ex bellis quaerere, &amp; regna regnis cumula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, qui non contenti Aſiae, Africae, &amp; maio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris Europae partis imperio, quicquid reliquum eſt praedae deſtinant: nec ſibi per religionem li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere aliter poſse opinantur.</p>
               <p>Videt haec <hi>M. V.</hi> ſingula, vnde &amp; hanc glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam eſt conſecuta, ambigentibus caeteris Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipibus quid ſentirent, ſolam
<hi>M. V.</hi> quid Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianae Reip. expediret, maximè &amp; vidiſſe, &amp; eligiſſe, autoremquè reliquis extitiſſe, vt, dum licet, mutuis auxilijs, communibus ſubſidijs tantae imaniſsimi hoſtis obuiam eant libidini, cuius opes inteſtinis ipſorum diſsidijs eô creuêrunt potentiae.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:13944:5"/> Perge porrò, Inuictiſsime Rex! &amp; hanc dextram non armis magis quàm pietate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, tuam ſidem imploranti, porrige Poloniae. Defenſor fidei es, commune Numen ne blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemetur, prouide; imitêre maiores tuos, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus haud graue fuit è proprijs Barbaros eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere latebris, &amp; vltimae Syriae finibus Britan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nici nominis gloriam terminare. Abundè am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſsimis
<hi>Maieſtatis Veſtrae</hi> ditionibus ſuppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunt, quaecunquè ad reprimendas potentiſsimi hoſtis vires requiruntur. Procerum copia, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli multitudo, omnis generis apparatus, vis immenſa; ne patiatur <hi>Maieſtas Veſtra</hi> peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimos rei militaris Anglos, bellicoſiſsimos Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos, Hybernos ferociſsimos, coniunctiſsimi <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſt. Veſtrae</hi> Regis, &amp; amiciſsimae gentis, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimina ſpectare otioſos, ac tàm latè ſerpens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendium in propriâ potiùs opperiri domo, quàm in vicinâ, dum licet, reſtinguere. In alieno diſcrimine propria curare pericula, nec prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentia duntaxat intueri, ſed futura proſpicere, erit celebratae
<hi>Maieſtatis Veſtrae</hi> prudentiae, erit &amp; magnanimitatis, quam vterquè admirabitur orbis, quam ſera praedicabit poſteritas, quam ſeruata venerabitur Polonia. Sereniſsimus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò Rex meus vti nunc particularem <hi>Maieſtatis</hi> 
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:13944:5"/> 
                  <hi>Veſtrae</hi> ergà ſe affectum, quâ poteſt maximâ animi gratitudine, complectitur, it à in poſterum cum ſe <hi>Maieſt. Veſtrae</hi> declarabit amicum, qui &amp; ſecundis <hi>Maieſtatis Veſtrae</hi> rebus ex ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo faueat, &amp; aduerſis, ſi quae impende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, non ſecùs quàm proprio com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueatur diſcrimine.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13944:6"/>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:13944:6"/>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Moſt Renowned KING,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE ſacred, royall Maieſty of</hi> Poland, <hi>and</hi> Suethland, <hi>my moſt gracious Lord and Maſter, wiſhing vnto your Maieſty perfect, and long health, moſt happy ſucceſſe in all your deſires, a flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and peacefull gouernment ouer your moſt large do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, declareth, by the moſt ample teſtification hee may of particular affection to your Maieſtie, the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular propenſion of a minde, brotherly, and moſt ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly addicted to your Maieſties affaires, and obligeth himſelfe by theſe Letters. And this Preface paſt, I moſt humbly beſeech your Maieſty, while I briefely declare the reſt of my Embaſſage, to vouchſafe me your benigns attention.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE long concealed poyſon in the breſt of the
<hi>Ottomans,</hi> hath now at length broke forth, and the maske of many yeeres faigned friendſhip laid aſide, <hi>Poland,</hi> the ſtrongeſt bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke of the Chriſtian world, is aſſaulted with the vniuerſall fury of the Barbarous. The Eaſt is filled with noiſe of preparation for Warre, the ſeas are loaden with Nauies, <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a</hi> is ioyn'd to <hi>Europe,</hi> and <pb n="10" facs="tcp:13944:7"/> what forces <hi>Affrica</hi> affoords, are arm'd for our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Into the ſociety of ſo great a Warre there come the hereditary enemies of our name, the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars;</hi> there comes alſo both the <hi>Dacians;</hi> the
<hi>Serui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Bulgars, Boſnians, Illyrians, Thracians, Epirotes,</hi> al wilde, and barbarous people whatſoeuer, by force, rewards, promiſes, hopes of prey, deſire of reuenge, are compel'd, allur'd, enraged. A lamentable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue to this bloudy tragedy hath lately bin acted; cruell <hi>Dacia</hi> hath greedily drunke the firſt bloud, where the perfidious enemy mindleſſe of his paſt and preſent leagues ſolemnely ſeal'd, and ſworne, inuading with innumerable troopes the territories of the King, my moſt clement Maſter, ſlue, to the ſingular loſſe of the Chriſtian Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monwealth, our ſmall, but moſt warlike Army oppoſed againſt him. For by that victory the courage of the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> chiefe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> at the</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ainſt</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ans, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>lemn
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>eir
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> for
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ceſſe
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e, the</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rke <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> them,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> from were
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r own
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſtroy</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> increaſed, and they growne inſolent with ſo happy beginnings, haue in hope deuoured all <hi>Europe,</hi> beeing ſo farre tranſported either with arrogance, or madneſſe, that euen without <hi rend="sup">a</hi> Gods aſſent, they beleeue themſelues able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy our Nation. With ſo great a danger not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of his owne, but of all other Chriſtian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, the Sacred Maieſtie of my moſt gracious Maſter being moued, hath determined with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to forewarne other Princes of the imminent <pb n="11" facs="tcp:13944:7"/> perill, but eſpecially, all delay ſet apart, to referre it to your Maieſtie. But ſuch is the ſingular vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilancy of your Maieſtie, ſo great is your ſtudy of the common good of Chriſtians, that you doe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſe them, to whom the dangers in reſpect ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of time, or place chiefely belong; and your Maieſtie preuenteth euen this meſſage of my moſt renowned King, &amp; of your own accord You haue offered what wee ſhould haue ſought, when to this ſelfeſame enemie, you declared your ſelfe Friend to the Regall Maieſtie of my moſt gracious Maſter, and that you would not forſake him in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny danger. Wherein his Regall Maieſtie acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth your truely great, truely royall, truely Chriſtian minde; vvherein hee acknowledgeth your Maieſties brotherly affection, vvhich with the teſtification of a moſt thankefull heart, hee embraces, and profeſſeth there is nothing ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, ſo difficult, ſo dangerous, which he vvould not likewiſe for your Maieſties cauſe vndertake. I vvould to God other Chriſtian Princes might be moued by this moſt famous example of your Maieſtie, and that they vvould rather be fellow labourers in ſo glorious a worke, then idle and ſlothfull ſpectators of others danger, ſince by neglecting their neighbours, they cannot but at length ruine themſelues. Which how likely it is to <pb n="12" facs="tcp:13944:8"/> come to paſſe, they may, if Heau'n bee pleaſ'd, beleeue, forewarned by the example of our ſelues, vvhom neglected <hi>Greece,</hi> forſaken
<hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> haue caſt into theſe preſent ſtraights. And ſurely vvee ſhall ſuffer vvhatſoeuer Heau'n im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth with reſolution to renew the examples of the <hi>Saguntines</hi> faith, <hi>Tyrians</hi> conſtancie, or of what fortitude hath elſe beene found; but let our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours forethinke how they ſhall prepare their mindes to endure the like, or (vvhich Heau'n for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid) greater calamities. Neither let them once i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine the Tyrant, whoſe minde the poore <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matian</hi> cottages drew to ſo deteſtable periury, wil eſteeme more holy the rights and lawes of neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood vvhich he ſhall make vvith them, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vvhoſe cities moſt flouriſhing in Merchandiſe, moſt excelling in riches, moſt beautifull in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, hee hath long gaped. Theſe things vvill not keepe backe, but draw him on, they will not quench, but inflame his ſacrilegious thirſt of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging his Empire by all both inhumane, and irreligious wickedneſſe. For vvho ſees not the Tyrant onely to intend that vvhich is knowne to haue beene long time debated in the counſell of his predeceſſors, that by poſſeſſing a country yeelding eaſieſt acceſſe into all parts of
<hi>Europe,</hi> moſt fertile of all kinde of graine, moſt reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13944:8"/> with all neceſſaries to build, and arme a Nauie, hee might open plentifull granaries to his numberleſſe Armies, and prepare infinite ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, by which beeing Maſter of the <hi>Balthike</hi> Sound, hee might paſſe into the Ocean, and ſo with two Nauies, as it were with two wings, by both the Seas, preſſe, and oppreſſe <hi>Europe;</hi> that he might through moſt open Countries, and Plaines powre into
<hi>Germany,</hi> by thoſe quarters it borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with <hi>Poland,</hi> his Land forces, where are no cloſure of Mountaines to reſtraine, no ſwiftneſſe of Riuers to fore-ſlowe his iourney? This, long ſince,
<hi>Solyman</hi> and his ſucceſſors caſt in their minde, neither were they, as it is manifeſt, by any other reaſon deterred from that purpoſe, then for that they beleeued, all Chriſtians would conſpire to defend that Kingdome, on whoſe ſafety the good eſtate of all <hi>Europe</hi> depended. Neither did there vvant in that age Princes ſo magnanimous, that they rather choſe to ſuffer loſſe of ſubſtance, yea of life, then to forſake the endangered ſafety of their neighbour Nation. But many in this our age apprehend not, with griefe I ſpeake it, theſe things, ſome neglect them, and which is more to be lamented, induſtriouſly inuite this faithleſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie of the Chriſtian name, of which they are
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13944:9"/> vnworthy, and then the Barbarous themſelues more execrable, to the common deſtruction of all. Theſe our times, moſt Renowned King! finde onely You, who in your ſingular wiſedome haue conſidered, and vnderſtood that all <hi>Europe</hi> is ſtrooke at through the ſides of <hi>Poland,</hi> and that the danger toucheth all Chriſtians; that to ſeeke Warres after Warres, and heape Kingdomes to Kingdomes, is cuſtomary with the <hi>Turkes,</hi> who, not ſatisfi'd with the Empire of
<hi>Aſia, Africa,</hi> and greater part of <hi>Europe,</hi> deſigne what e're remaines for prey, and according to their religion, imagine it is not lawfull for them to doe otherwiſe. All theſe things your Maieſtie well ſees, and thereby hath attained the glory, whiles other Princes ſtand doubtfull what to thinke, alone to haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and choſen what was behouefull for the Chriſtian Common-wealth, and to haue beene Author to the reſt, of reſiſting, by mutuall aides, and common ſuccours, the ſo great rage of a moſt cruell enemy, whoſe fortunes haue growne vnto this height of power by their inteſtine diſcords. Proceede then, O moſt inuincible King! and reach out this your hand, not more knowne by Armes then Piety, to afflicted <hi>Poland</hi> imploring your helpe. You are Defender of the Faith; take <pb n="15" facs="tcp:13944:9"/> then care that our common Deity be not blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; imitate your Predeceſſors, vvho held it not burthenſome to rowze the Barbarous out of their owne dens, &amp; ſtretch vnto the bounds of fartheſt <hi>Syria,</hi> the glory of the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> name. In your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties moſt ample Territories all things abound which are requir'd to repreſſe the force of the moſt potent enemy; ſtore of Nobility, multitude of people, prouiſions of all kinde, immeaſurable power. Let not your Maieſty ſuffer the <hi>Engliſh</hi> moſt experienced in military affaires, the moſt warlike <hi>Scotſh,</hi> the fierce &amp; moſt couragious <hi>Iriſh</hi> idly to behold the dangers of a King moſt ioynd in friendſhip, &amp; of a Nation moſt-affected to your Maieſty; and rather to expect in their own roofes ſo large a ſpreading flame, then, whiles they may, extinguiſh it in their Neighbours. To prouide in others danger for your owne, nor to caſt your eye only on preſent, but alſo on future things, belongs to your Maieſties celebrated Wiſedome, belongs to your Magnanimitie, which either world ſhall admire, which long poſteritie ſhall report and praiſe, which preſerued <hi>Poland</hi> ſhall reuerence. And my moſt Renowned King, as for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent hee imbraceth with all poſsible thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the particular affection of your Maieſtie <pb n="16" facs="tcp:13944:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> towards him, ſo in all time to come, he will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare himſelfe that Friend, which ſhall from his ſoule both fauour your Maieſtie proſperous ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, and in aduerſe, if any ſuch ſhould chance, be no leſſe mooued then with his proper danger.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13944:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
